Finding Aid for Standish Backus papers, 1919-1942
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Standish Backus papers 1919-1942
Backus, Standish.
1 oversize volumes
4 linear feet
85685 Aa 2; AC
Detroit, Michigan, businessman, president of the Burroughs Adding Machine Co. Correspondence and reports relating to the Kelsey Expedition to the Near East for the University of Michigan and correspondence files, 1926-1942, concerning business affairs and social activities in Detroit and Grosse Pointe, Michigan; also writings of father Charles K. Backus, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The bulk of the collection came from Mrs. Standish Backus (donor no. 2625 ).
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Standish Backus was born in Detroit on January 12, 1875. He received his B.A. degree from the University of Michigan in 1898 and graduated from the Detroit College of Law in 1901. Following a seven year period in the private practice of law, he joined the General Motors Corporation as counsel in 1909 and became Secretary of that corporation in 1911. In 1917 he became Director and Vice-President of the Burroughs Adding Machine Company and succeeded to the presidency of that company in 1920, which office he held until his death on July 13, 1943.
In addition to his business interests, Standish Backus undertook a portion of the expense of University of Michigan professor Francis Kelsey's archeological expedition to the Near East in 1920.
The Standish Backus collection consists of correspondence and reports relating to the Kelsey Expedition to the Near East for the University of Michigan and correspondence files, 1926-1942, concerning business affairs and social activities in Detroit and Grosse Pointe, Michigan; also writings of father Charles K. Backus, and photographs. The Photographs include portraits of members of the Backus and Standish families, and of Mr. and Mrs. Joseph Boyer.
The collections is arranged into five series: Kelsey Expedition to the Near East; Correspondence files; Personal and memorabilia; Charles K. Backus volumes; and Photographs.
Subjects:
University of Michigan Near East Research Expedition (1924-1934); Backus, C. K. (Charles K.); Burroughs Corporation.; Detroit (Mich.); Grosse Pointe (Mich.); Kelsey, Francis W. (Francis Willey), b. 1858.; University of Michigan--Archaeological expeditions.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Backus, Standish.; Backus family.; Boyer, Joseph, 1848-1930.; Clothing and dress--1860-1880.; Demonstrations.; Detroit High School (Detroit, Mich.); Gamma Delta Psi Fraternity. Iota Chapter (Detroit Central High School); Interiors.; Psi Upsilon Fraternity. Phi Chapter (University of Michigan); Standish family.; University of Michigan. Class of 1899.; University of Michigan--Societies, etc.; University of Michigan--Students--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; University of Michigan--Student housing--1891-1900.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- Kelsey Expedition to the Near East
  - 1919 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1920 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1920 (Box 1)
  - 1921-1923 (Box 1)
  - 1924-1926 (Box 1)
  - Miscellanea 1920, undated (Box 1)
- Correspondence files 1926-1942
  - Colburn, F.S. (Box 1)
  - Colman, F.B. (Box 1)
  - Costikyan, K. (Box 1)
  - Cottrell, G.W. (Box 1)
  - Cram, R.A. (Box 1)
  - D (Box 1)
  - Darrow, Emily [estate] (Box 1)
  - Derrick, Robert O. (Box 1)
  - Detroit Edison Co. (Box 1)
  - E (Box 1)
  - Earle, Mrs. D.M.K. (Box 1)
  - Essex Scottish (Box 1)
  - F (Box 1)
  - G (Box 1)
  - Gamma Delta Psi (Box 1)
  - Gooch, C.W. (Box 1)
  - Gow Co. (Box 1)
  - Grant Central Art Galleries (Box 1)
  - Griswold Research Co. (Box 1)
  - Grosse Pointe Club (Box 1)
  - Grosse Pointe Club-Board of Governors (Box 1)
  - Grosse Pointe Unitarian Church (Box 1)
  - Grosse Pointe property (Provencal Blvd.) (Box 1)
  - H (Box 1)
  - Hammond Standish & Co. (Box 1)
  - Hildebrandt, N. (Box 1)
  - Holden Co. (James S.) (Box 1)
  - Home (proposed)-early material (Box 1)
  - Hope Ranch (Box 2)
  - Hornblower & Weeks (Box 2)
  - Hotchkiss School (Box 2)
  - House of Peters (Box 2)
  - Hudson Nurseries (Box 2)
  - Jewett, E.H. (Box 2)
  - K (Box 2)
  - Keane, W.L. (Box 2)
  - Kelsey, F.W. (Box 2)
  - L (Box 2)
  - Leland, W.C. (Box 2)
  - Lunken (E.F.) Family-Cincinnati (Box 2)
  - Lynch (Kenneth) & Son, Inc. (Box 2)
  - M (Box 2)
  - Mc (Box 2)
  - Manny, Walter B. (Box 2)
  - Macauley, Alvan (Box 2)
  - Marks, Virginia B. (Box 2)
  - Medieval Academy of America (Box 2)
  - Michigan Bell Telephone Co. (Box 2)
  - Michigan Society of Mayflower Descendants (Box 2)
  - Midland Bank (Box 2)
  - Miller, Ruby B. (Box 2)
  - N (Box 2)
  - Claude Neon Lights, Inc. (Box 2)
  - 0 (Box 2)
  - Olympia Skating Club (Box 2)
  - P (Box 2)
  - Pfaelzer, F.T. (Box 2)
  - Pom-MC Fate Co. (Box 2)
  - Princeton University (Box 2)
  - Princeton University (Chapel Window) (Box 2)
  - Priscilla Inn (Box 2)
  - Q (Box 2)
  - R (Box 2)
  - Roberson, Charles L.
    - Furnishing (Box 2)
    - Contract for interiors (Box 2)
    - Personal (Box 2)
  - Roumania (Queen Marie) (Box 2)
  - S (Box 3)
  - Salisbury School (Box 3)
  - Seyffert, L. (Box 3)
  - Singing Beach Trust (Box 3)
  - Songs (Box 3)
  - Spalding, E.B. (Box 3)
  - Sprague, E.L. (Box 3)
  - Standard Oil Co.-Detroit (Box 3)
  - Standish, Marian and W. Colburn (Box 3)
  - Steele, Fletcher
    - 1929-1932 (Box 3)
    - 1933-1934 (Box 3)
    - 1935 (Box 3)
    - 1936 (Box 3)
    - 1937-1938 (Box 3)
    - 1939 (Box 3)
  - Steele, Fletcher, miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - T (Box 3)
  - Taxes (Box 3)
  - Todhunter, Inc. (Box 3)
  - U (Box 4)
  - V (Box 4)
  - Village of Grosse Pointe Shores (Box 4)
  - W (Box 4)
  - Walker (Ethel) School (Box 4)
  - Waldo, Frank (estate) (Box 4)
  - Whipple, J.C. (Box 4)
  - White Allom & Co.-New York (Box 4)
  - Witenagemate Club (Box 4)
  - Woodward Baptist Church (Box 4)
  - X-Y-Z (Box 4)
- Personal and memorabilia
  - Book of notes and poetry 1899 (writer unknown, probably Standish Backus) (Box 4)
  - Clippings, newsletters and congratulatory letters concerning Standish Backus' election to the presidency of Burroughs Adding Machine Company 1920 (Box 4)
  - Burroughs Bulletin (scattered issues), 1926, 1930 (Box 4)
  - Book: To Thomas Alva Edison and Guests in honor of the golden jubilee of the invention of the electric light; also accompanying booklet, 1929 (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook, 1895-1900 of Detroit High School and University of Michigan memorabilia, including photographs and clippings, 1895-1900 (Volume 1)
  - Loose items from scrapbook (Box 4)
- Charles K. Backus volumes
  - The Nassau Literary Magazine February 1861 including an article, "Mirabeau" by Charles K. Backus (Box 4)
  - The Michigan Teacher magazine 1876 including an article, "An Outside View of the Public Schools," by Charles K. Backus (Box 4)
  - The Contraction of the Currency 1878 by Charles K. Backus (Box 4)
  - Harper's New Monthly Magazine March 1882 including the article, "An American King" by Charles K. Backus (Box 4)
  - The International Review December 1882 including an article, "A Picture of Northwestern Development" by Charles K. Backus (Box 4)
  - Bound volume 1884 of obituary notices and sermons on the deaths of John D. Standish and Emma L. Standish (Box 4)
  - Personal memoranda volume 1889 of personal reminiscences, family history, and clippings of Standish Backus (Box 4)
- Photographs
  - Backus, Charles K. and Evelyn Standish (Box 4)
  - Backus, Cyrus and Dorliska Kellogg (Box 4)
  - Backus, Mary E. (Box 4)
  - Backus, Standish
    - Early photos (Box 4)
    - Portraits (include 1899 U-M class portrait) (Box 4)
  - Boyer, Joseph and Clara (Box 4)
  - Standish, John, and family (Box 4)